[Music]
you're listening to the AI native Dev
brought to you by
Tesla hello everyone welcome back to the
AI native Dev podcast I am guy pajari
and today I'm here with itamar fredman
who is the co-founder and CEO of codium
AI who are probably one of the top
leaders in the AI test generation World
we'll talk a lot about that and they do
a lot more than that and has a very kind
of varied and interesting background
notably has worked on verification in
melanox and sales before working on sort
of Chip verification and domains in
which testing and making sure you got it
right is a lot more serious or taken a
lot more seriously than in software
Tomar welcome on to the podcast thanks
for joining us here thank you for having
me and congrats on the new exciting
podcast definitely an opportunity to
have conversations with interesting
people like yourself so I guess let's
jump right into it tell us a little bit
about what what is AI test generation
and then later on we'll dig into into
what codium does within that world but
what is AI test generation and and why
is it a topic now like why how does it
work yeah so first of all testing or
verifying that code works as expected is
like a huge problem already specifically
I can tell you that I was in charge at
least 49% in charge of a bug and one of
the corporates I worked in that cost
cost the company $88 million just an
example and by the way I think like it's
one of the biggest bottleneck and
productivity I think like we many of us
experience that 50% of the work the user
Sprints sorry the Sprints the user
tickets is related to bugs Etc so it's
already a problem and testing is one way
to try to overcome this problem trying
to reduce the amount of bugs that are
introduced the low quality code Etc
having said that I think testing is is
just one word that describes a full
field there's many types of and classes
of testing I'll keep it short just to
start with like the unit testing
component testing integration testing
system testing endtoend testing Etc and
I think like in many of these there are
some inefficiencies and and many if not
100% of of these testing types there
there are inefficiencies that AI could
help with uh some of them is like
actually in the plan in the planning of
the test like even the strateg
strategizing how to test some of them is
creating data for testing some is
generating code or scripts for testing
some are actually could be like around
AI selecting the right tests to run for
a certain user story or a certain change
in code so AI could really boost and
make it feasible to to exploit testing
which we couldn't do before I think
everybody would want to do testing I
think everybody tries to use testing and
I think it we didn't solve the problem
of low bad quality code or bugs in
production all of us experienced like I
mentioned so I think that AI is about
first Ai and testing is about first
identifying what how to test your code
what is the right strategy and then
again applying AI to generating tests
and maintaining those tests over time
yeah those are really important
distinctions so we talk about AI test
generation and maybe I I just leaned
into the hey it writes a bunch of like
unit test code on it but you make very
good points which is it's actually
broader than that and choosing what
needs to be tested where does it test
and I guess in all of these cases the
reason we say AI versus planning is
because of the fluidity why do we need
AI for this in theory software is fairly
deterministic right it runs well like
why what is the unlock that AI brings us
that we didn't have in more
deterministic systems
you you mentioned my past experience
working on uh cheap verification Etc and
harder verification so I think like
there when you think about a certain
module and and Hardware it's Mo mostly
described with a very clear
specification with bits in bits out
literally bites in bites out and you can
even use formal verification like
mathematical proof and and in order to
say okay this works as expected but I
think that with software although it's
like you mentioned it's deterministic I
think the input output is human in human
out the definition is could be like
given a PRD or like product requirement
definitions or document from a product
that might not might not be like for
formal formally covering all the happy
paths edge cases Etc might actually be
even vager what it means and the same
goes I can describe the output so
basically the fact that software in most
cases the interfaces and the outcome is
supposed to serve people as human in
human out brings the opportunity to and
actually the I think the must have ai to
cover those those cases where you need
to communicate with people so I I think
that it's if you really try to cover all
the option like you're trying in
Hardware covering all the option or at
least sufficient option to make sure
that you don't have any bug then you're
having two problems doing that for
software one is that it's really
inefficient it could be like a nightly
job for testing everything might not
cover all the options that you want to
cover maybe different than a certain
model and module and hardware and the
second thing is it's not necessarily
clear what are exactly all the options
that you need to cover and again like AI
could help you in and both like deciding
what are those like happy path and edge
cases that really worth testing and then
I actually helping to generate those
tests which is most people like you
mentioned thinking about that AI will
help you generate tests but what are a
good test what is a good test and then
eventually like also choosing
efficiently by the way like a small
Story related related to what we just
talked about like I heard a friend like
actually a client eventually saying that
like he pushes his team to have 80% code
coverage and and then one team reached
85% code coverage and he was like really
surprised he went checking and and he
saw that there's no asserts like
basically test were covering a lot of
lines of code uh but there weren't like
weren't asking any questions in the
process yeah we really check anything
except that if it fails like it crashes
or not crashing it will check but not if
the outcome functionally wise is working
as expected I think that's something for
example that will almost won't happen
like in hard verification because the
definition itself input output but could
help Happ happen to teams and and
software so that's even the fact that
software is deterministic there's still
a lot of test smells and and and knowhow
and how to do testing and AI could
actually help with that even yeah so
interesting so I think you mentioned
maybe two I hear two big categories over
here one is this Gap in the definition
of what's right and what's not right and
so AI can help us deduce from the code
what is it that you intended to do maybe
with a help and we're going to talk a
little bit about attended versus
autonomous test generation but it it it
helps you understand that gap which is
it hasn't been stated precisely unlike
maybe in chips and their definition what
is it that is the correct behavior and
so does it and then the second is the
kind of infinite realm or overly large
realm of possibilities that softer
allows because of its flexibility help
us choose the paths that that matter
more and that we should focus on or we
should that maybe represent broader
sequences is that right like we haven't
gotten at all into a generation of I
guess all of this is not yet necessarily
geni this is just like AI you might it
might manifest as gen AI but it it is
still around Insight here get AC correct
because let's start with the second part
because basically you can't it's not
most software is not just about a
certain algorithm where by the way
Hardware is like almost you can almost
like do a p code of algorithm even for
let's take quality of service module in
a Nick like in a network like card Etc
it's almost like writing an ALG and you
can try to prove it and while in many
other type of software like business
logic of different kind you can't like
literally explicitly write some
mathematics to in many cases to prove it
by the way maybe in crypto whereas there
I think opportunity for AI by the way to
introduce like more formal because it's
more formal because it's and it deals
with things that are it's not like you
can cover it's not that triv trivial to
to analyze what is the minimal flows
that you you need to cover in order to
promise with a pack for a certain error
you you're you're 99% sure that you you
covered everything so so definitely it's
a big part but and and also about the
generation part I would I claim that
actually writing generating like the
event the eventual 10 lines of tests is
not the hard part of about writing tests
I'm not saying that AI can help there it
definitely can help there but actually
more important is what is what you want
to test what's the the business logic
what's let's describe it first in
natural language description what is you
wanting to describe and then you can use
like another step in in the flow of
using AI to actually generate the code
but let let me say it in different words
when we're talking about AI generating
test roughly speaking dividing into two
what do we want to test and then
generating that test I'm claiming that
generating that test is a challenge but
actually a harder part is describing a
natural language description what is
that we're trying to test here what are
you trying to test comes from what is
the intent what is this piece of
software trying to do you need to fetch
this information from specification from
your documentation from other pieces of
code and then how you want to test
what's the flow you can still describe a
natural language description what is the
data do I need to pull push pull it from
the database to to bring the right where
is the right structure to to what is the
right output it's not yet the code it's
like a logic that you need to write and
then eventually you can convert it into
code which could still be challenging
because you need the right Imports and
the right mocking and and things like
that but both steps are and are very
challenging and I would claim that even
the first is more challenging yeah so it
it it sounds like it because it's a
broader space but there's maybe like a
bit more margin of error here or
flexibility you can make maybe seven
decisions while when you generate
there's an expectation of accuracy right
maybe let's dig into that so we said
when we talk about AI use in testing it
starts from understanding what it is
that you
want to do so that's one and then
there's another layer that is still
before the Gen part uh which is
understanding what tests need to be
generated to be able to verify that
there are an infinite set of
possibilities so what type of data how
does the system behave what are the
states like all that information and
then subsequently after all of that you
need to go off and generate a test and
that's the even newer field because I
guess there have been a few kind of
startups in the space trying to do the
AI Insight piece before and I think gen
was the unlocker around making it usable
right because if the if a system comes
back to you and says here I figured out
the Thousand tests that you should write
you're going to say thanks but so long
I'm not going to do that and so I think
that last piece of making it usable and
actually being able to generate those
tests is a big deal no that's the that's
at least the Gen unlock that allows
companies like K come in and be useful
to to a customer you know what I'll make
it interesting I think I
disagree I I'll but I'm not doing it
just to make to make it interesting I'll
give you an example let's be concrete
let let's say for example we talked
about different types of of testing
we're talking about for example we talk
about end to end testing and let's say
that we want to do the end to end
testing on the UI okay let's again I
want us to be able to imagine think
about an e-commerce I don't want to say
a name but choose one of the e-commerce
that that you use and now let's say that
they're developing a new feature with a
click of a button it automatically let's
think about 2024 automatically collects
you want to buy a certain item and they
want to develop a new feature that with
a click of a button it collects your sim
similar product that you bought and will
bring you to the to buy something that
is like this item but already choosing
the right color for you when displaying
you the this item to to purchase on on
on the buying page so um I you could say
okay maybe the hard part if I take what
you say like maybe the hard part is
actually generating the script that that
creates I don't know the playright the
Cypress whatever script that actually
Runs run this kind of of test but I
claim that actually the harder part is
to think about all the relevant flows
that I want to test this feature and
think about the work of a QA tester like
usually like the more it goes lower to
the code like the unit testing component
testing integration testing you see the
developers doing that work and the more
more that you go to the end to end
mobile and interface you see more like a
QA team or a q QA automation team by the
way I think that's going to shift left
you thanks to AI but maybe not for
another point the first thing they do
and I think it's actually one of their
hardest is think about all the flows
that that needs to be checked eventually
I claim that when a when a bug is being
eventually introduced to production it's
not because they didn't know how to
write the code or they didn't have the
time to write the code they just forgot
or didn't think about different flows
they can come with oh there was already
one of these item in the carts and I
didn't think about checking that option
Etc so I know there are solutions and I
know there are products but I actually
claim that gen not just AI has the
opportunity here to to reinvent in and
like this field as well for example if
if you give a gen the opportunity to
crawl this already exists before gen to
to crawl over different parts of your
website and understand user Behavior and
then generate flows like invent flows
take the the description from the
product manager and take all the
experience of crawling the website prior
to that and generate flows of testing
and then eventually also generate the
test itself so I just I'm claiming here
that gen is also going to be introduced
in the first part of analyzing what you
want to test and how you want to test
and I think it's very
important I think that's I don't know if
we're entirely in disagreement I guess
my sense is that this last part is not
not the hardest but it is the grunt work
that if you created a thousand of those
items they will not get done what we've
seen at sneak for instance was yeah if
if you came along and you said here are
a thousand dependency updates that you
need to do and they are you know very
easy to do or relatively easy to do
maybe there's a check around the system
if you don't actually you really need to
hand it on a silver platter of here's
the precise change that you need to do
to mobilize people and even go to the
distinct to the level of having that be
automated and done for them and it's not
out of any ill will and it's not because
it's hard but it's because it's tedious
it's because it's not a task that people
want to do and they definitely don't
want to do it repeatedly so I I agree
and it's interesting maybe to to have us
Define a bit the the Gen piece I don't
know if that's the most useful thing for
us to do there is the Gen piece of of
the llms of understanding the system
which we're using so that is a new breed
of AI which is bucketed into gen because
it's a part of the sort of new breed of
Technology but it's not generative in
nature it is more analytical still and
doing it and then you have the
generative piece of okay now I'm
actually creating a thing that would
flow through them but I think point
taken which is you have to understand
the applications you have to understand
what what was meant to be correct you
have to understand these sort of
possible States and the flows within the
system you have to decide that and then
at the very kind of last step you need
to actually maybe write some code or
selenium script or whatever it is some
flow that would actually execute and
interact with the application by the way
I agree agree with you I I'll give you a
concrete example like I think it's
interesting one so very shortly so I
agree with you like in some cases you
know what you want to do but actually
executing that gen like actually enables
that and I'll give you a concrete
example we talked a lot about testing
but actually one of our second or maybe
I would say it's hard to say which one
is our strength point at Codi is code
review and and actually working around
like increasing the quality of a polar
Quest almost another artificial eyeballs
and uh to describe a poqu and and review
it Etc and here here is an example that
fits really well to what you describe in
many cases companies they already know
that they need to revamp certain a
certain old they want to modernize if I
call it like an like Gardner word they
want to modernize a certain piece of
their code and they already by by the
way have symbolic or other type of tools
that are not necessarily eye that tells
them give them a recipe on how to
modernize a certain a certain like a
spring two to three or whatever it
is yeah but then like they need a gen to
close some some of the final final
changes they need AI to make a final
review they need like the last mile of
what you mention I know what we want to
do we want to modernize we want to
revamp we want to refactor disart I know
that's what I want to do because what I
claimed that AI could help you
understand what to refactor just an
example what we talked about I know what
we want what I want to do but actually
taking the last mile on closing some
additional piece of code like a few
lines of code that are not part of the
recipe and also making like giving a
last review you need AI because I
probably in a big corporate 10,000 of
developers I probably need to do it so
many times I have to make it efficient
for reviewers to already have ai to
close to review the first few things so
that's one of the our use cases and it
fits to what you say so I also g a few
so I would say that's probably how the
worlds divide like those use cases and
challenges where it's actually hard to
understand what actually want to test
what actually want to change and then
there's that the part that actually if
you don't have the generate generative
part to to execute it you you can't
actually uh officially efficiently
provide the value on it yeah so maybe
let's shift gears a little bit and talk
ined about the types of tests that
you've mentioned in passing over there
because I think probably some of this
the importance of different aspects of
this defer based on the types of test
you rattle them off but what would you
say are the primary categories of tests
yeah I'm going to talk about sharing
about different type of test I also like
shake a bit the boat about their
importance I think there are times that
people described levels layers of
testing with a triangle and sometimes as
a diamond I think originally the the
triangle was the most common shape that
was accepted and I'm which means that on
the bottom you have the unit test and
then on top of that you're building like
component test it's like a bit more than
a unit and then on top of that you have
sorry just for for for the sake of some
of our fellows listener although I guess
99% aware unit tested means like taking
four lines of code taking the smallest
component smallest element of of a class
or even it could be even a sub function
with within a function or so and trying
to tie the test that will verify that
this piece works as expected isolated
the most isolated way would probably
work the best for for unit test they're
fast and then you have a bit on top of
that like component test usually like
more if you want like rule Su like a
class like where you can even describe
like a the the shortest flow in your
software um and while unit test tend to
be very technical in nature component
tests start to some intent so there's
some intent but an intent is relatively
still very technical very like software
a certain very small piece of software
very agree with you I'm Aline with you
and then on top of that you're starting
to start to deal with microservices it
could be like traditionally four
component but it's just like a nice
number but it could be two component
connected together it could be 100
component connected together but it's a
microservice that's now actually serving
some business full business logic a full
application could be one microservice to
to many as well but it's one of them
actually performing some service and
there in these cases usually you have
integration tests Etc there there are
more types but just an example that's
that's the middle of the of the triangle
on top of that you have System test and
an endtoend test UI testing Etc where
where you actually what you do is to try
to test the entire application the
entire system Etc there more more
Dimension and more additional different
type of coloring we can we can do here I
didn't talk about functional test
nonfunctional and things like that but
that's roughly the one way to look on
the TR and I think some people would say
and I think it's was more and more
common in between 2010 to 2020 that
actually the right way to look at is
that diamond and most like value is in
the integration test and I think one of
the reason is because it's sorry it's
hard to do unit testing because
it's so rigorous you you need to go
function by function it's also hard hard
to maintain it but I claim that actually
AI might change that a bit and make it
easier to do unit testing and make it
easier to maintain them that maybe
eventually like we will go back to that
that that triangle is the way to look at
it I I I think that division makes sense
but it it always refers to just the unit
size or the kind of the scope that
you're testing what about the notion of
regression tests versus functional test
I think we both put aside the
non-functional test so there's just
performance testing security testing a
variety of those types of tests I guess
we're putting them out of scope for this
conversation for a moment
but within I always find important to
talk about the source of truth right
because we talk about how AI helped you
understand the intent or what is the
what is it that you're even supposed to
ask and what is the correct answer what
is the correct behavior all of those are
very functional that's those are hard
things and they they all revolve around
the source of Truth being the user's
intent of of some sort but regression
tests are different right regression
tests the source of Truth is really the
previous version and it's almost you
even want to preserve the bugs on it I
guess see them as the same how do you
delineate uh the two in in concrete
terms yeah I I love this topic really
roughly speaking I would like I love
your definition like what's source of
Truth really roughly speaking we can
when we're looking on that Dimension we
can divide into two one is that we want
to test a new functionality and and it
could be different sub subtype of tests
there and or we want to test that we're
not breaking anything and there could be
a few types there for for example
regression test is like checking
specific behaviors like functionalities
and the integration level unit test
level that what what we knew that
already should have work that we didn't
break anything like there's no
regression we could also someone can put
also smoke tests and and others also in
this category basically I'm making some
change in my code and I just want to
check that some simple I don't know
input provide me some simple output by
the in these tests for example smoke
tests Etc not necessarily checking
behaviors intensively but there they
checked you didn't break something big
like the the basic functionality is
working yeah so I think definitely it's
worth considering that in general and
also when you're talking about AI why
because when you're using Ai and you're
talking about more on the regression
testing then the code is NE is like a
very useful source of truth you're
saying this should work how could I test
that but when you're talking about
testing new code that you want to enter
actually your source of truth that you
need to relate to is the natural
language description it could be like a
struct one like bdd behavioral like
business description of certain types
but I think that there's a lot AI like
can really enjoy from the fact that code
is a formal language that you can
actually compile when you're talking
about new code that is the Sor of Truth
is the natural language description that
might be formulated to some extent it's
still not formal language and then it's
like brings uh opportunity for for
mistakes so definitely when you're
you're thinking of either building a
product to generate test with AI or
you're using AI to generate test you you
will see different even behaviors sorry
I want to say different behaviors but
even might be a different uxui right
where does it reside like in the ID or
in your jira but also the interface
itself one might might look like much
more rigorous and one might look like
more a chat just an example yeah I think
so maybe let's switch a little bit to
talk about trusting
AI generated tests and it's a tricky
topic so we classified these types or
you classified these types of tests that
grow in scope from the unit to the
component to the microservice to the
integration that clearly requires a more
holistic understanding of the system and
a knowledge of it and then there's
regression tests and maybe there are
smoke test maybe they're a little bit
easiest to know what's failure in all of
those cases you need to know what is
correct and the problem is that
typically to know whether it is correct
cor or not we use tests so if you wrote
the tests then you can do all sorts of
wild stuff behind the scenes and
eventually you know you would generate
something and you would test and you
would see if it's correct but if you're
using AI if you're rolling the dice to
generate the test in the first place how
do you know what to trust what is the
means of verification the trust but
verify the verify is supposed to be with
the tests how would you
define the way that people tackle that
concern today first of all do you agree
with this being a challenge and then how
should someone deal with trusting AI
generated tests today yeah first of all
I very agree with that and immediately I
can't not stop thinking about uh
different memes and Proverbs like hey
who QA is the QA and saying like that in
the essence this is a very someone needs
to be the authority eventually of saying
this is correct versus not yeah and in
specific typically that's a very known
like term sorry pert like like a problem
like who QA is a QA who how do you trust
that a QA actually qate everything Etc
so in essence I agree with you like good
eventually you you need it's the buck
needs to stop somewhere and the question
is does it stop in the AI or stop in the
developers it's one of the question that
raises they raising here but another
before I actually try to answer or or
more seriously relate to that I want
another another aspect to say
like food for thought I think basically
what we're talking right now I can ask
differently like how do we solve
software I think if it's almost the same
question what you just answer what you
just asked me how do we solve software
how do we like generate software that
just works I think it's almost the same
question because that's what testing is
meant to do and code review and by the
way Sol solving software it's again it's
not just working code it's performing
it's secured it's maintainable it's
extendable it's it's according to our
company's best practices according to
our values of the company I'm not
kidding I think it's software
development is actually relat to also
company's values especially in the era
of AI but tests but tests are like I I
agree the tests are a necessary part of
how do we solve software but they're a
part of it solving software also
requires you know better definition of
what it is that is correct also implies
thinking about the evolution of software
and how does it change over time of
course it implies the actual writing or
generation of the code and and a variety
of other aspects of software I guess I'm
like we still have a low resolution the
critical part of it is that whatever it
is that you do you need to be able to
say is it correct or not but it it it
doesn't you can solve this and not yet
solve
software the the point you said that was
was my point I'm saying eventually
testing is a part of it you want tests
because you you want to to know that
your software works but I claim that the
testing is our common way to do that our
that's what we're biased towards to
because that's what we did for 20 years
but probably a it's not the only way and
and B it's probably you're still it's a
sub problem you want to check that your
code works but eventually why do you
want to check if your code works because
you want to make sure that you're not
harming your users and that you can move
fast with confidence Etc and there are
other aspects that you need to consider
if you want to do that but anyway now
back to to be to being how do you trust
it how do you I guess yeah we should
also talk a little bit about maybe like
sources of information for it but for
starters like if I'm a user I'm
generating a test like yeah know it
right how how does a system how does the
company or the organization know that
those AI generated tests are trustworthy
great so now to be concrete because I
think like the philosophy here is
important because we we want to
understand why we're doing what we're
doing I before I'm going to answer you I
promise in two points but I I do want to
give you like an example what I'm
talking about um what about uh doing
test lless testing what about like T
taking the uh taking the specification
that you wanted to to have for example
let's say that a certain technical
product manager did describe really well
what you want to achieve in in the
software or or a developer but I'm just
like for a sake for example a technical
product manager described con like
concisely but actually precise with high
accurate elaborated specification what
about taking the code and what you
actually generate are not tests you take
the code and generate spec out of it and
then you do spec matching so the process
is generating spec that is the same
format of the spec that was generating
by the technical product manager and
then running a matching algorithm could
be AI could be gen we can talk about it
and and tell you what's where's the
mismatch hey here's test testing to but
not the old way but the new way that is
enabled thanks to generative AI so I I
that's why was was important for me to
to go to the essence why we're doing
testing at all we want to check that the
software Works according to our
requirements according to our best
practices and not just okay this piece
of code pass a test okay now let me be
concrete I think there there are two
things that we need to double click in
order to test your testing one is that
usually in most cases in order to for an
AI system or assistant to generate
meaningful test usually it it's not
performed by gathering a bit of context
and doing one inference call usually
there is a full flow real product that
actually works or works sufficiently
well for you to to useful for you they
you're using a a full flow and by the
way I love to double click about later
we released the Codi released a couple
of these flows as as open source and we
even reached state-of-the-art codenation
be doing better than professional
competitors on coding competition doing
better than deep mine openi Etc and the
concept that was different than other
competitors like deep mine and openi
that we designed a flow okay back to my
point to actually generate good tests is
designing a flow flow and then what you
can do is surface as a person that
developing this these tools you can
Surface the decision that were made as
part of this flow and as a user as a
developer you can review this the
process that was done on the path to
generate this final test and this gives
you more
confident you can gain confidence by
reviewing the process that was done on
the process let me give you an example
I'm going to give a simple example to
make it make it s and clear for example
as part of the process the system might
look for other mocking that that is
already implemented in and and trusted
because they run as part of the cicd or
whatever and choose to use them as part
of generating those tests as a developer
if I see that this mock was not
generated right now it was actually
taken from another piece of testing
another test site that is I know that I
trust and then I'll probably trust this
new test that's based on that and we
like it or not like I mentioned testing
is if you do perfect testing you know
exactly what to cover and you generate
test perfectly this is solving software
so it's not easy okay so it's not
there's isn't a magical answer yes I
trust AI because it gave me a confidence
number or because it did it five times
correctly no it's the same process that
you would do with a developer you would
see the syncing process you would see
the pr description you would see the and
then you learn to trust this this output
and that's number one and the second
thing is that relating to the intent if
you see some connection like you see the
test and and the AI system shows you
this test was generated because here's
the intent that I'm relating to and here
is how the implementation actually
covers this intent I think this is also
will give you confidence so these are my
I think the main two points that that
you need to look and when you're
choosing a solution or as a developer
developing these systems I think those
are are useful kind of steps towards it
they they include first of all they rely
on attendant I'll use the opportunity to
say that of course one more thing that
if the test run if if it compiles if it
doesn't break anything and by the way
this is what meta released in their work
test test llm gen sorry have a blackout
I think that's how they call it and we
reproduced their work they didn't
release open source for it we released a
work called cover agent test gen llm
sorry where their way to provide you as
a developer confidence that the tests
are good to create they have more but
two two part parts that the test builds
and run and that increase code
coverage okay but no notice that this
works only for regression test the fact
that test builds and runs doesn't break
anything in your system and actually
increase coverage is only for regression
test okay so there's more tactical thing
that you can do perir test type
regression unit test you can do for
example what meta said but in high level
it's what I said showing you the process
and showing you that you actually did
something meaningful like increasing
code coverage you increased the coverage
of the intents and Etc yeah and I think
there are once again the different
layers of it right the first part of it
is agreeing on what needs to be tested
and you gave the example of the spec but
really that spec itself needs to be
verified and back to an attended process
someone needs to uh look at that and say
it's correct and then subsequently you
need to generate the test and see that
it passed and so code is a little bit
better maybe than other gen domains
because you're able to run the the code
itself and see what has occurred so the
very that it's functional I guess
there's still a leap though about okay
what you need to test and you've
generated a test that runs but does this
test actually confirm that the
requirement that I've defined is correct
and then subsequently you talked about
the implementation piece of it and maybe
delegating some of that trust by saying
hey there's an already trusted mock for
instance and so that's more like I've
probably manually attended verified that
is correct and therefore I am building
on top of that and I'm able to to trust
that is as correct and all of that are
even ahead of
the broader lens of are these tests like
find coverage is one measure of it but
are these the right tests to be running
so because you can Define sort of an
intent I guess there's those are all
compelling and there's still a lot that
is saved and at the end of the day if
you have all of those then you're able
to develop with confidence whether
you're developing with AI or manually or
whatever you however you're doing it
but there's a lot of attended process
over here right there's a lot of
verification yes there's human errors
but there's also the goal here was to
take the tedious Parts away to be able
to generate these things we haven't even
opened up the sort of the maintenance
piece of it how what's the path to
autonomy what's the if we're thinking a
little bit further out and we say this
is the attended test generation process
that happens today that saves you a lot
of time but still requires a lot of
human attention maybe with the exception
of regression tests which are making the
leap of faith that the current way of
running is correct and so you can have
this external source of truth that is
scalable it's the existing system what's
the path to to more autonomy in the
world of test
generation yeah okay okay so let me let
me first answer a question about
autonomy but actually it relates also to
other what we just talked in the
previous question so I think despite
like amazing videos that we saw on X
Twitter amazing demos that we see I
don't know on on stages Etc practically
most of this agents that are autonomy
like they're generating some software
given a certain
intent this piece of software that
generating is very simple I would even
claim that most of these demos you
probably have a certain repo that you
can find on gab that does very exactly
that or very similar so you can probably
in five minutes do the same thing if you
just and then the and by the way maybe
it does transform it a bit to it's like
almost like recall like the right piece
of code it was drained on but also
transforming into your specific request
so there is some magic there is some
good thing about it but it it's it's not
closed to even like slightly closed to
generate anything useful for Enterprise
okay at the same time I claim that in
five years we will see an AI developer
in Enterprise I'm calling that that demo
that we're seeing like an AI developer
okay some some people call a engineer
but that might be confusing aine or
something tweaking AI for so an AI
autonomous AI developer we will see
something for that but only in in three
five years the earliest and here is how
I think it's going to happen I think
we're going to see a a first AI tools
being integrated into different parts in
already in the existing software
development tool chain processes
workflows for example our PR agent is
connecting to your GitHub gitlab bit
bucket Etc sorry for the Shameless plug
here but it's I really believe what I'm
saying and it helps you already
reviewing your code verifying best
practices Etc and then for example you
have another tool that connects your ID
helps you do the testing and then
another tool connecting to your cicd and
helping choosing the test and then
another AI tool connecting to your
builds and helping you analyze the logs
of failures and once you have these are
all AI assistants right these are all
they're not at I I'll keep it right now
in the AI assistant realm although I
think we can say that they could be also
AI agents but what I'm saying here that
even if they're agents they're going to
perform very small yet critical
subprocess in the overall workflow of
software development they might actually
be agent they might actually choose for
you automatically which test to run they
might even analyze the build error and
try to suggest you an an option to fix
it fix it build again see that it passes
Etc so it might be agents but we're
going to have like many of these flows
again I'm referring to what we call Flow
engineering as the way to develop useful
agents um and then suddenly uh maybe
sudden uh po moment maybe not when we
cover like a certain portion 80% 90% I
don't know maybe it needs actually to be
95% of this sub processes sub workflows
with AI integrated in them suddenly you
can build an additional agent an
additional AI autom AI developer that
will work with the I don't know
technical product manager will get and
work with that manager on the intent
like formalizing
perfectioning to some extent the intent
and then that agent would be able to
generate that software because the
guardrails agents the an the Angels
guarding Angels the other AI that were
worked really hard to integrate to the
right databases to the right Frameworks
to the right best practices to the right
Etc will can can have the feedback loop
and Perfection like that that's how I
that's one option and another option is
to reink so this is before we go to the
other option is this one is more this is
much more so I guess what you're
describing here is I don't want to say
incremental but it is about correct get
better help us as an industry or let's
as an industry get better at doing every
one of these bits as they worked today
like the code completion stuff and all
that that would generate code that
better interprets intent the code review
will work better at spotting mistakes on
it the cover agent and and its similar
tools will help us test and identify
whether a change has broken on it codei
itself would help us build sort of
functional test around it always in sort
of an intended fashion and then in
analyze logs and so we'll build all of
that sort of Journey of of these
different steps getting better and
better and then eventually when all of
those work together then we have enough
confidence to build something and that's
tricky
because when you build a lot of these
different pieces if each of them works
at a 95% accuracy if you chain 10 of
them it's going to be broken half the
time right like whatever the multiples
work over there but it is I guess it's
the easiest one to imagine right like
it's let's just get better at each one
of these steps and then at some point
okay all I've done is I've when I find
myself every time just saying yep you're
right yep you're right y you're right at
some point okay just just assume you're
right and proceed and I'll fall back if
it seems like you were wrong this time
am I describing the process like this
path of evolution you talked about is
the the I don't know if it's a linear
path but it is the gradual path yeah I
agree with you and by the way I also
agree about the disadvantages of this
approach you
know we can claim that it's broken or
not fully exploiting AI so you're
actually just like trying to to do the
best you can with what exists and the
other option is to rethink it but it
actually could be like a past that will
not converge eventually if there is some
process some subprocess in the workflow
that AI won't be able to overcome and
that's if that subprocess cannot be
overcome or cannot be automated with an
agent then you won't be able to to pass
this you will still have a some
resistance to actually move to the
autonomous AI developer the advantage of
of this approach is that look it's
probably really freaking hard for an
Enterprise to say hey we're throwing all
the dozens of tools if not more that
we're already using and the processes
and the workflows and and everything and
and to change something completely
completely new I'm not saying it didn't
happen I think we can find cases in in
the past especially if that thing is
like pics but it's hard so that's a
disadvantage on sorry that's the
advantage of taking this
approach and by the way one more reason
and It's Tricky what I'm going to say
but I think we're might a little bit
exaggerating with what AI can do right
now okay and then maybe it's more
feasible actually to take like small
parts and in current workflows and
trying to improve that at the same time
get real value get it's not the fact
that it doesn't jump to autonomous
doesn't make it not valuable not by a
long shot like these tools coding today
the code completion like they are
massively valuable today they make
people more productive so they're very
valuable in their own right which is
another advantage of the gradual path
which is you're already going to be
doing it because there's immediate
benefits to be had yeah at the same time
again a
might actually maybe the path to
autonomous like needs to be like we need
to rethink and I can think about a few
points that maybe yeah so let's talk
about that let's so let's maybe close
off the podcast the other way around and
say okay let's say we didn't increment
our way to it but we managed to throw
the thing away and reimagine the
software development process and maybe
let's still put um a certain lens on the
sort of the testing or verification
aspect of it but how would we do this
better if we were to to reimagine the
process yeah so I think like you see my
repeating notion here that we want
testing whether especially if it's not
ression if we want to test new code is I
think it's all about the intent yes I I
agree with you like what we talked if we
close the loop with what we talking
about uh half an hour ago that
eventually ji gives you the opportunity
to uh do the last mile of I know what I
want to test and then it's actually like
I have 1,000 of these and I couldn't do
that without gen but I still think that
in most cases actually one of the
hardest problem problem is to start with
having the right in having a a a good
intent having a testable intent having
uh an intent a spec that is already
anchored in and with the current code
I'm developing new code and my new
specification is already anchored while
I'm writing it while I'm invent
inventing it while I'm creating a new
user story Etc it's already anchored in
the language in in in the way I describe
it as a for example as a technical
product manager to my code so to rethink
everything the software
development also in with the Spectrum
when focusing on testing and and
verification it's a lot about the intent
working with AI and Reinventing how we
as R&D and and product as as a whole uh
thinking about how do we write our our
specification how do we we Define our
intent how to exploit AI to already
create a PRD or a spec a technical spec
or a product spec that could be more
easily already to start with work
exploit AI to then generate the code and
generate the test and generate the
review and Etc if we rethink that part
then we would make it easier for AI than
also to complete the code and complete
the testing and complete the
verification yeah and I think clearly
I'm in line right when we talk about AI
native software development we think
about sort of spec Centric software
development and how that centers it
today like you you mentioned at various
points this notion of looking at the
code and first understanding maybe it
comes from that PRD from someone who's
written it maybe it comes from the
understanding of the code and create an
understanding create a spec of sorts in
the brain of codm somewhere in the
process that says this is how it works
but in today's software development
process the tests
are that specification right there is no
interim there's no at least commonly
used interim representation of those
intents they come hand inand with the
test of the implementation as well good
for me because that's really to
something I wanted to talk about like
previously and then it connects um uh
okay there's no one way to to test
things like we said like ideally test
are menant to verify that the the intent
is actually being implemented but
actually because there's no like formal
way to do that in in in in software in
most cases like unless it's like an
algorithm or so that can prove
mathematically there's a few ways to to
do that and different companies and
different teams have opinions about it
so a lot about like the generating tests
and giving confidence that these tests
are good ones is actually generating
those tests according to the best
practices that were given by the
developers so one of the thing that that
for example is enabled in kodum PR agent
and as an example is that a team can
give a markdown hey here's how we would
like the testing style to be to be in
this repo and this is how the testing
style will like to be in in that repo
once you make uh testing en once you
enable an AI uh Dev tool to generate
test work according to your best
practice working according to your test
t
and then if that tool works well enough
to quite easily I'm not taking saying
with the click of a button but much 10
100 easier than it was was before to
generate test then yes test could be uh
your source of tools uh uh for for the
spec some CTO that I talked to told me
that their preferred documentation is
actually working tests so that's align
with what what you said like
documentation as there's a whole tdd
world that really talks about tests
being at the center of the universe I
agree with you but like I mentioned
again it's it's not magic it's not like
just okay AI will generate those tests
and here's my new spec no we need to
build a tool that generate those tests
according to a specific style that your
Dev team and even your product managers
technical one would consider as a spec
and then if we can make those test
executable specs which test in in your
style in your and easy for you then we
can actually rethink rethink specs
executable specs yeah yeah no well
clearly align our view over there and
it'll be interesting there's a lot to
probably unravel that we might do in
sort of future conversations on the
evolution of those specs and how do they
change and how do they relate to data it
this has been fascinating thanks a lot
for coming on for sharing I do encourage
everybody to check out we didn't talk
too much about kodi's products on it but
there's a bunch of good free tools out
there in agent PR agents and I guess
actually most of the solutions that you
have tomorrow are have a free tier of a
way for people to to experiment to try
out with and then expand into into a
premium version right correct our ID
agent which we call Cod mate our git
agent which we call PR agent like our
git plug-in our ID plug-in our CLI
plug-in our they have the Cod mate PR
agent cover agent names that they're all
either they're all free and some of them
are even open source we have just one
component that we didn't yet find a way
on how to move it towards the the free
which is our full codebase analysis like
we you you can give the Codi platform
you can provide it like 10 10,000 repos
and we run like different analysis and
we do want to shift some part of it into
the free offering but it's still on the
work yeah it's okay you have to pay the
bills and some yeah so i' encourage
everybody to try it out and tiptoe their
way into this into this Brad new world
of AI generated tests with a its great
promise and some complexities and some
adaptations we probably need to do as
humans itar thanks for coming in to
share all this insight and knowledge
with us thank you g that's pleasure I'm
happy that we talked mostly about
interesting stuff Cod is one tool of I
think exciting one set of tool one
platform of the exciting intelligent
coding system that I I think we're going
to see in the future and then thinking
about how we as developer imagin that I
think that's what exciting and then the
tools are here to just enable that
awesome and thanks everybody for tuning
in and I hope you join us for the next
one thanks for tuning in join us next
time on the AI native Dev brought to you
by Tesla
[Music]